Guide to the Francis M. Dimond Mier Expedition Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mier Expedition Papers
1843-1844
WA MSS S-497
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.5
(1 box)
The bulk of the collection consists of letters to Francis Dimond concerning members of the Mier Expedition held prisoner in Perote, Mexico.
Dimond, Francis M.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Thomas W. Streeter.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Francis M. Dimond was United States Consul at Vera Cruz, Mexico. The bulk of the collection consists of letters to Francis Dimond concerning members of the Mier Expedition held prisoner in Perote, Mexico.
Prisoners -- Mexico; Perote (Mexico); Public officers -- United States; Beesley, D. H. E.; Berrien, John MacPherson, 1781-1856; Bugg, William; Calvert, James; Conger, James; Dimond, Francis M.; Dobbin, L.; Dusenbury, John E.; Fisher, William S., fl. 1844; Gibson, Alexander, fl. 1844; Gibson, William, fl. 1844; Green, Thomas J. (Thomas Jefferson), 1802-1863; Johnson, Chauncey; Müller, F. William; Oatts, Harvey H.; Pleasants, Martin; Rhea, John, fl. 1844; Riddle, John, fl. 1844; Ryon, William M.; Smith, Ezekiel; Smith, Thomas S, fl. 1844; Tatum, Thomas S.; White, Thomas, active 1605; Texan Mier Expedition ( 1842-1844)
- Box and folder list, 1844 May 14
  - Beesley, D. H. E. ALS to F. M. Dimond. Castle of Perote., 1844 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Writes on behalf of 9 other prisoners.
  - Berrien, John Macpherson. LS to F. M. Dimond, U.S. Consul at Vera Cruz, Mexico. Washington, D.C., 1844 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Encloses money for William Bugg, member of the Mier expedition, now a prisoner at Perote.
  - Calvert, James. ALS to Francis M. Dimond. Castle of Perote, Mex., 1844 Jul 31 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Note on p. 3 signed: Wm. Ryon.
  - Conger, John. ALS to F. M. Dimond. New York., 1844 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Concerns prisoner John E. Dusenbury.
  - Dobbin, L. ALS to F. M. Dimond. New Orleans., 1844 Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Concerns money for prisoner Oatts.
  - Fisher, William S. 3 ALS to Francis M. Dimond. Castle of Perote, Mex., 1844 Jul 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gibson, Alexander. ALS to F. Dimond. Cincinatti., 1844 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Concerns prisoner William Gibson.
  - Johnson, Chauncey. ALS to John Riddle. Perote, Mex., 1843 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Muller, F. William. ALS to Genl. [T.] J. Green. New Orleans., 1844 Jan 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Recommends that Francis Dimond, U.S. consul at Vera Cruz, be granted land in recognition of his efforts on behalf of Texan prisoners in Mexico.
  - Pleasants, Martin. ALS to Francis M. Dimond. New Orleans., 1844 Jul 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Concerns prisoner Thomas S. Tatum.
  - Rhea, John. ALS to F. M. Dimond. Castle of Perote, Mex., 1844 Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ryon, William M. 5 ALS to Francis M. Dimond. Castle of Perote, Mex., 1844 Apr 22 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Smith, Ezekiel. ALS to F. M. Dimond. Santiago Prison, Mexico, 1844 Jun 23 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Smith, Thomas S. ALS to Francis Dimond. New Orleans., 1844 Jun 24 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Concerns prisoner Thomas White.